בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ט"ו. Tes Vav. Today
everybody today's דף daf is ט"ו, Tes Vav, we pick up on
י"ד עמוד ב' Yud Dalet Amud Bet at the bottom. We're going
through the process of bringing of the מנחה mincha of the סוטה,
sota, and I don't know if anybody read the email that דוב
לב אריה Dov Lev-Aryeh sent out last night, but I was right
it's גרש, geres, not גרש, geres, by the way, מגרסא. migirsa. So
thank you for S-A-M for sending that out. Anyway, you know what
they say last time I saw last time I thought I was
I was wrong I was mistaken. Okay, so
anyway. Alright, so
anyway, we pick up here
at two lines from the bottom, ומלקט את לבונתה ונותנה על גביה,
umalket et levonata venotnah al gabav, two lines from the bottom last
line on י"ד עמוד ב'. Yud Dalet Amud Bet. So this is
the actual the normal process of bringing a מנחה mincha we quoted
a ברייתא brayta about that before we circle back to talking about
the bringing of the מנחה mincha of the סוטה. sota. So gathers
up the לבונה levona now that he's put the קומץ kometz the
handful of the מנחה mincha in a separate כלי שרת kli sharet
in a separate vessel holy vessel he now the כהן kohen gathers
the frankincense and he from the מנחה mincha and transfers it from
the original מנחה mincha vessel where the מנחה mincha is to the
vessel where the קומץ kometz is which he's going to offer up
on the
מזבח mizbeach כדכתיב ואת כל הלבונה אשר על המנחה. kichtiv ve-et kol
ha-levona asher al ha-mincha. And the לבונה levona which is on the
מנחה mincha he offers up on the altar so now he transfer
so he gathers that excuse me and now that becomes now part
of what is going to be offered. ומעלה ומקטיר בכלי שרת umaale
umaktir vachli sharet the top of ט"ו עמוד א' Tes Vav Amud
Aleph and he brings it up to the to the top of
the altar and he offers it up from the holy vessel. בכלי
שרת מקטיר ליה bachli sharet maktirei is what is he offering it
up in the כלי שרת? kli sharet? So it sounds like the
גמרא's Gemara question is that he's throwing כלי שרת kli sharet into
the fire but רש"י Rashi actually
says has a different גירסא. girsa. רש"י Rashi says מקטירה סלקא דעתך
maktirah salta da'atach like how at this stage is it say he
offered it up if the next line is that he salts it?
So he hasn't offered it up yet. אלא אימא מעלהו בכלי שרת
להקטירו. ela eima maale vachli sharet lehaktirou. He's bringing it up in
the כלי שרת kli sharet to offer it up which A says
that he's not offering up the כלי שרת kli sharet and B
also says he hasn't burnt it he hasn't burnt it up yet
he first has to salt it which is the next line. ומולחה,
umolcha, welcome back Dov. And he salts it. ונותנה על גבי האישים
venotnah al gabei ha-ishim then puts it on the fire דכתיב וכל
קרבן מנחתך במלח תמלח. dichktiv vechol korban minchat-cha bamelach timlach. And all
of you know all of your מנחה mincha קרבנות korbanot you shall
salt and salt is on all the קרבנות. korbanot. And then קרב
הקומץ שיריים נאכלים karev ha-kometz sheyarne chalim because it was a ברייתא
brayta that was quoted that described the order of bringing the מנחה
mincha which was in order to clarify or anyway it's just helpful
background if we're talking about the bringing of the מנחה mincha of
a סוטה sota number one it's helpful background so I under well
no but not everything is straight in the פסוקים pesukim the stuff
that's straight in the פסוקים pesukim it doesn't elaborate on the stuff
that isn't it elaborates on. Okay.
So he's bringing it like a ברייתא brayta from the this the
other just the regular bringing of a מנחה. mincha.
It's not a ברייתא brayta yesterday we started with the fact that
the משנה Mishna said that a normal מנחה mincha starts in a
כלי שרת. kli sharet. And we said it's not true a normal
מנחה mincha doesn't start in a כלי שרת. kli sharet. Look at
this ברייתא brayta that describes how a מנחה mincha is brought and
it says that you start by bringing it from vessels from the
home and you don't start in a כלי שרת. kli sharet. And
therefore that led to the modification fine a normal מנחה mincha doesn't
start in a כלי שרת kli sharet it starts in a vessel
fit for a כלי שרת. kli sharet. But in that context we
quoted a whole משנה Mishna actually ברייתא brayta actually that gives the
entire סדר seder of bringing a מנחה. mincha. So now we're just
finishing elaborating that ברייתא brayta which is helpful which we spent a
lot of time on a lot of things anyway here it actually
is helpful to provide a background if we're going to spend time
about bringing of the מנחה mincha of a סוטה sota let's have
some background about how a normal
מנחה mincha is brought. One minute can
you
repeat that
please?
No. קרב הקומץ למר כדאית ליה ולמר כדאית ליה. karev ha-kometz lemare
kiseh lemare kdis leh. Now the קומץ kometz being brought when is
it considered to have been brought that's a debate of תנאים Tannaim
exactly the stage when it's considered to have been like burnt up
when it's considered to have been הוקרב hukrav like offered you know
and accepted as a קרבן korban like the act is done. When
is that? So let's take a look. איתמר הקומץ מאימתי מתיר שיריים.
itmar hakometz me'ematai matir shiyarayim. When does the handful make the remnant
the remainder of the מנחה mincha permissible to be eaten? באכילה be-achila
to be eaten? רבי חנינא
אמר משישלוט בו האור Rabbi Chanina amar mishe-tishlot bo ha-ur once the
fire is like has dominance over it like once it's caught האור
ha-ur fire. רבי יוחנן אמר משיצת האור ברובו. Rabbi Yochanan amar mishe-tatzit
ha-ur berubo. It says
that once the fire has actually caught hold to the majority of
it. So which seems to actually be actually it's an interesting question
I was actually assuming you know that this is I think that
this is a further stage that it actually has to not just
like have you know have caught on fire but actually taken hold.
hold of the majority of it. Okay. ושאר הכהנים ליתן לתוכו יין
ושמן ודבש Vesha'ar hakoanim litein letocho yayin veshemen udevash and then continuing
in the ברייתא, baraita, the כהנים kohanim can mix into it wine
and oil and honey and they can put anything into it as
long as they don't let it become חמץ. hametz. So the גמרא
Gemara says מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אמר קרא amar
kra למשחה, lemoshcha, it says that it should be for you for
a, literally for an anointing, but it means like for a, for
something of status, לגדולה legedulah for some, for
you should treat it like in the way of affording status the
way you eat it, כדרך שהמלכים אוכלים. kederech shehamelachim ochlim. You can
eat it in a, you know, in a way that's a, that's
a, that's a respectable way, a refined way, a way that shows,
you know, a person of, I'm saying the word status again. Anyway,
that's what a king would eat, exactly. So therefore you can eat
it, you can eat it, you don't have to eat it because
you could have thought, look, it's a, you know, it's a קרבן,
korban, therefore, you know, you shouldn't mix with it things that are
not קרבן-like, korban it's not respectable for the קרבן korban to be
putting on things, you know, other foodstuff, you know, maybe you're like,
you know, you're taking away from the מצוה mitzvah of eating a
קרבן, korban, you're making it just like a meal and you're making
it a fancy meal. You have to maybe, you would think maybe
you have to focus on the thing itself. So no, you're actually
allowed to eat it in a way that, that is respectable way,
that makes it tasty, that makes it, you know, like a king
would eat. That's acceptable, just don't make it into חמץ. hametz. Okay,
now, which raises an interesting question, right, because how much of these
can you actually make חמץ hametz if they've already been baked? Now,
how is it possible to actually make it חמץ hametz once it's
been baked, which is a whole interesting discussion what next time we
learn מנחות Menachot we can talk about it. Okay. ואינה אסורה אלא
מלהחמיץ ve'einah asurah ela milehachmitz
and it's only forbidden to make it into חמץ. hametz. דכתיב dechativ
לא תאפה חמץ lo teafeh hametz do not make it חמץ hametz
and the end of the פסוק pasuk is חלקם נתתי אותה מאשי
chelkam natati otah me'ishai their portion I have given to them from
my fire offerings, from my fires, but the דרשה derashah is לא
תאפה חמץ חלקם lo teafeh hametz chelkam do not make even their
portion into חמץ hametz not only the מנחה minchah as when it
begins don't let it become חמץ hametz but even after it's been
offered and you're only left with the remnant, that remnant cannot be
חמץ. hametz. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish
אפילו חלקם לא תאפה חמץ afilu chelkam lo teafeh hametz even their
portion cannot be allowed to become חמץ. hametz. Again, again harder to
understand exactly how that's possible. I mean there's one מנחה minchah which
isn't baked which is just, you know, but and then the question
to that מנחה minchah that isn't baked is then how does it
not become חמץ hametz anyway if it's just a mixture and then
the ones that, you know, but of course if it doesn't have
water if it just has oil, so okay, but the ones that
are baked how could it become חמץ hametz after it's already baked?
Anyway, so these are all interesting questions when you learn מנחות Menachot
there's like a whole פרק perek devoted to the איסור issur of
חמץ hametz for מנחה, minchah, yes.
Right just a quick visual, so we say baked, but really it's
like a laffa on coals, directly on coals, correct, on the altar,
not what we would call baked inside an enclosed-
Yeah, well, yeah, that's true, I shouldn't have said baked, I mean
it's maybe cooked or whatever. I mean there are different ones, there's
the מנחת מחבת minchat machavat and the מנחת מרחשת, minchat meracheshet, but
that's right, it's more, it's more like, you're right, it's more like
it's been on a fire like- It's not been baked in an
oven.
Well yes there is, there's a
מנחת מאפה תנור minchat ma'afeh tanur that is true, you know,
anyway, it's why מסכת מנחות masechet Menachot is so long.
Yeah. Okay. So, all right, כל מנחות, kol menachot, now, now we're
now Michael's going to be happy because we're done with this ברייתא
baraita which more belongs to מנחות, Menachot, but gave us general background,
and now we turn back to the מנחת סוטה. minchat sotah. And
it says all of the מנחות menachot have oil and, and frankincense
with the exception of the מנחה minchah of a סוטה sotah and
again, because to just show how, you know, lowly it is, and
this is brought for a sin, and the other types of things
that the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara here asks וכל
המנחות טעונות שמן vechol hamenachot te'unot shemen what, is that really true
that all מנחות menachot need oil ולבונה ulevonah and frankincense? והאיכא מנחת
חוטא vehaika minchat chotei how about the מנחה minchah of a sinner
at the, at the end of פרשת ויקרא, Parashat Vayikra, not ספר
ויקרא, Sefer Vayikra,
there's a series of קרבנות korbanot which are called עולה ויורד oleh
veyored which means variable, you know, goes up and down based on
a sliding scale, based on what a person can afford, a handful
of sins that you bring this type of a חטאת chatat for
and at the end, the bottom of that sliding scale, if you're
very poor you just have to bring a מנחה minchah and that's
called a מנחת חוטא. minchat chotei. So there actually is a normal
sin for, a normal חטאת chatat offering is, is an animal. Okay.
But is a, but for this particular sin you're allowed to bring
series of sins, you're allowed to bring, depending if you're, if you're
of a lower economic level, so, status, you're allowed to bring a
מנחה minchah as the, as the sin offering and that is called
a מנחת חוטא. minchat chotei. And the גמרא Gemara says that also,
and this is so it's not really different from any מנחה minchah
of a sin, and this is also seen as a type of
a מנחה minchah of sin, although here the sin is suspected, not
known, but it's seen as any type of a מנחה minchah of
sin. So what makes this special? והאיכא מנחת חוטא vehaika minchat chotei
רחמנא אמר rachamana amar לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה.
lo yasim aleha shemen velo yitein aleha levonah.
Actually the פסוק pasuk is quite explicit, right? כי מנחת קנאות היא
מנחה- ki minchat kenaot hi minchah
am I quoting the סוטה sotah one? Okay. So what's the פסוק
pasuk here by- that's true, it's the same type of verse, but
what is the פסוק pasuk here? You want to- so I go
to have to look up the פסוק? pasuk? כי חטאתי. ki chatati.
Thank you. Okay. Because it is a sin offering. So anyway, very
similar verse. So anyway, so it's no different than a normal מנחת
חוטא. Minchas Chotei. So גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. No,
no, no. Okay, you're right. It's not like it's the only one
that doesn't have שמן ולבונה. shemen ve-levonah. But what it is is,
it is the only one that has all of the disabilities if
you would, all of the things that make it a less sort
of, you know, status type, a less significant type of a מנחה.
mincha. And here's what it says. Here's how to read the משנה.
Mishna. כל המנחות טעונות שמן ולבונה, Kol ha-menachos te'unos shemen ve-levonah, all
מנחות menachos have oil, and, you know, oil and frankincense ובאות מן
החיטין, u-ba'os min ha-chittin, and come from wheat flour ובאות סולת, u-ba'os
soles, and come from refined flour.
And what it really means is, all of the מנחות menachos have
at least one of these, you know, positive qualities that make it
nicer. Some have all, some have only one, but all of them
have at least one of these qualities. מנחת חוטא, Minchas Chotei, the
מנחה mincha of a sinner, אף על פי שאינה טעונה שמן ולבונה,
af al pi she-eina te'una shemen ve-levonah, although it doesn't have oil
and frankincense, באה מן החיטין ובאה סולת, ba'a min ha-chittin u-ba'a soles,
it comes from refined wheat flour. מנחת העומר, Minchas Ha'omer, the מנחת
העומר, Minchas Ha'omer, אף על פי שהיא באה מן השעורים, af al
pi she-hi ba'a min ha-se'orim, it's true it's not wheat, it's barley,
אבל טעונה שמן ולבונה ובאה גרש, aval te'una shemen ve-levonah u-ba'a geres,
right גרש? geres? Okay, so
it comes from oil and frankincense and it's refined barley flour. So
actually, all the other even the exceptions have two out of the
three qualities. וזו, Ve-zo, and this, doesn't have any of those three
of the three qualities. אינה טעונה לא שמן ולא לבונה, Eina te'una
lo shemen ve-lo levonah, it doesn't have oil and frankincense, ובאה מן
השעורים, u-ba'a min ha-se'orim, and comes from barley, ובאה קמח, u-ba'a kemach,
and comes from bran and not from refined flour. Okay, so it
is true there are some things, it's not true that any one
of these as it were negative things doesn't exist by another מנחה,
mincha, but other מנחות menachos at least don't have all three, at
most they have, they'll have only one of these negative qualities, this
has all three of these like lower qualities. Yes.
And despite the fact that it's an awful
מנחה, mincha, כהנים Kohanim still have to eat it.
Besides the fact, yes, that's true. Okay.
So the כהנים Kohanim are getting penalized.
Phew, maybe just mix it with a lot of oil and just,
a lot of, just mix it with a lot of oil and
whatever exactly. And honey etc.
Ezekiel bread. Oh my gosh. Okay. Alright. So, okay. Alright.
Bran by the way, is that what you said?
Really? Yeah, the opposite of סולת. soles. קמח Kemach means, it doesn't
mean only the bran, it means like whole wheat actually, whole, פשט,
pshat, whole, I meant with the bran, with the bran.
Okay, right, with the bran. Okay. Alright. תניא, Tanya, right. אמר רבי
שמעון: Amar Rabbi Shimon: ודין הוא שתהא מנחת חוטא... Ve-din hu she-tehei
Minchas Chotei...
now this is very interesting. ודין הוא שתהא מנחת חוטא טעונה שמן
ולבונה. Ve-din hu she-tehei Minchas Chotei te'una shemen ve-levonah. Really, the תורה
Torah should have demanded that a מנחה mincha of a sinner, not
of a סוטה, Sota, a normal מנחה mincha of a sinner, should
have had oil and frankincense. Why? שלא יהא חוטא נשכר. She-lo yehei
chotei niskar. Why does he get off easy that he doesn't have
to do the extra expense of the שמן ולבונה? shemen ve-levonah? Of
course it's funny, he also gets to bring a מנחה mincha rather
than a more significant one. But okay, within the context that this
is what he could afford and he's bringing a מנחה, mincha, it
should have had the demands of a standard מנחה. mincha. Why does
he get off easy? אבל מפני מה אינה טעונה, Aval mipnei mah
eina te'una, why does it not demand it? שלא יהא קרבנו מהודר,
She-lo yehei korbano mehurdar,
that it should not be beautiful and that's more important, the symbolic
significance of what he's being brought than the fact that we're imposing
on him a greater financial demand. ובדין הוא שתהא חטאת חלב טעונה
נסכים. U-ve-din hu she-tehei Chatas Cheilev te'una nesachim.
And in principle, by a similar argument, a sin offering of fat.
Now why is it called a sin offering of fat? Because what
it means is a standard חטאת. Chatas. A standard חטאת Chatas is
brought for a sin that is חייב כרת. chayav kares. And a
sort of classic example of a sin would be forbid, even forbidden
foods, except it's funny, all the things that we normally think of
in terms of forbidden foods, most of them are not חייב כרת.
chayav kares. בשר בחלב Basar be-chalav is not חייב כרת, chayav kares,
חזיר chazir is not חייב כרת. chayav kares. The basic forbidden foods
that are חייב כרת chayav kares are חלב, cheilev, דם, dam, וחמץ
בפסח. ve-chametz be-Pesach. נבלה Neveilah isn't חייב כרת, chayav kares, okay. So
a sin, no, yeah,
but that's like a קדשים kodshim type of thing. גיד הנשה Gid
ha-nasheh is not. Okay, so anyway, so the standard way the גמרא
Gemara refers to a standard sin offering is a חטאת חלב. Chatas
Cheilev. So anyway, okay, where were we?
And רש"י Rashi actually points out in this רש"י Rashi that it's
not just a classic example but actually it's a juxtaposition of the
פסוקים. psukim. Because if you take a look at רש"י חטאת חלב,
Rashi Chatas Cheilev, he says כל חטאת סתם קרוי חטאת חלב, kol
Chatas stam karui Chatas Cheilev, דבתר הכי כתיב דכתיב כל חלב וכל
דם לא תאכלו, de-basar ksaiv dichsiv kol cheilev ve-kol dam lo socheilu,
וכתיב
בתריה פרשת חטאת, u-chsiv basrei parshas Chatas, that the פרשת חטאת parshas
Chatas actually is written
juxtaposed to the חלב cheilev issue. Now that's not because the focus
of the פרשת חטאת parshas Chatas is about eating חלב. cheilev. That
place where it says כל חלב וכל דם לא תאכלו kol cheilev
ve-kol dam lo socheilu is where it's talking about the fact that
חלב cheilev and דם dam go on the מזבח mizbe'ach and it's
in the middle of a discussion of the קרבנות. korbanos. It's not
in the middle of a discussion of מאכלות אסורות. ma'achalos assuros. But
nevertheless, right juxtaposed to that, near that, comes the discussion in the
תורה Torah of a חטאת. Chatas. Okay, but it means a standard
חטאת. Chatas. Okay, ובדין הוא, u-ve-din hu, and really logically speaking, what...
Because חלב ודם סמוכים chelev v'dam smuchim is where it's talking about
the fact that חלב chelev and דם dam go on the מזבח
mizbe'ach and it's in the middle of a discussion of the קרבנות.
korbanos. It's not in the middle of a discussion of מאכלות אסורות.
ma'achalos assuros. But nevertheless, right juxtaposed to that, near that comes the
discussion in the תורה Torah of a חטאת. chatas. Okay, but it
means a standard חטאת. chatas. Okay, ובדינו u-v'dino and really logically speaking,
it would have made sense to say שתהא חטאת חלב טעונה נסכים,
she-t'hei chatas chelev te'unah nesachim, that also a חטאת חלב טעונה נסכים.
she-t'hei chatas chelev te'unah nesachim. It would have made sense, you know,
would have made sense to say שתהא חטאת חלב טעונה נסכים she-t'hei
chatas chelev te'unah nesachim
that also a חטאת חלב chatas chelev should have had the the
what do you call it the the the libation sacrifices that come
together with an animal sacrifice, you know, it would be like we
read every you know when we say מוסף, Musaf, right? We say
you know we always after reading the קרבן korban we say you
know we read what the נסכים nesachim would be, so much wine
and then so much oil and so much flour etc. So so
it says it made it would have made sense that it would
have required נסכים. nesachim.
But why not, let me see where we are, ונימא אינה טעונה
u-neima einah te'unah why does it not, שלא יהא חוטא נשכר she-lo
yei choteh nishkar so the sinner should not merit so I'm sorry
I skipped I'm sorry I'm sorry. ומה טעם שתהא טעונה נסכים שלא
יהא חוטא נשכר u-mah ta'am she-t'hei te'unah nesachim she-lo yei choteh nishkar
so the sinner should not merit how come he gets off of
bringing נסכים? nesachim? ונימא אינה טעונה u-neima einah te'unah
why does it not require? שלא יהא קרבנו מהודר she-lo yei korbano
mehudar that it should not be beautiful. Now until this point he's
just giving a טעמא דקרא. ta'ama d'kra. He's not saying any הלכה,
halacha, right? Why is it that this doesn't happen? I mean why
does the guy get off, right? So the answer is because of
the symbolic sort of you know the symbolism is more significant than
whether he's spending more money or not spending more money. But now
the גמרא Gemara does an interesting thing, okay, or maybe he's doing
an interesting thing and let's keep on reading. וחטאתו של מצורע ואשמו,
v'chataso shel metzora v'ashamo,
this seems to be still part of the same statement of רב
שמעון, Rav Shimon, the חטאת chatas and the אשם asham of a
מצורע metzora טעונין נסכים te'unin nesachim
that does bring נסכים nesachim לפי שאינן באים על חטא lefi she-einan
ba'im al chet that's not coming for a sin, that is actually
you know it's coming for a purification process, it's not coming for
the purpose of a sin and therefore it gets נסכים. nesachim. Now
this is interesting because is this descriptive or is he actually learning
out from his טעמא דקרא? ta'ama d'kra? You know what I mean,
right? Is he you know is he sort of saying I figured
out that the reason for the difference is about whether it's based
on a sin or not? In principle even חטאות chatasos should demand
it like every קרבן korban in principle should demand it but there's
a question of the symbolism. So if you were to find me
a חטאת chatas that was not about sin then logically that that
actually should have נסכים nesachim and lo and behold so therefore that's
what so is he saying that's what we'll say by the חטאת
chatas and אשם asham of a מצורע? metzora? Like we're not learning
it from any פסוק. pasuk. I mean is he doing this based
on טעמא דקרא, ta'ama d'kra, right? Is he you know is he
doing it based on טעמא דקרא? ta'ama d'kra? He's just figuring out
that that should be the הלכה halacha because that makes sense or
is he describing it? No, we start knowing that a חטאת chatas
and an אשם asham of a מצורע metzora bring נסכים nesachim and
now I'm going to explain you the reason why.
So if you actually take a look at I think רש"י Rashi
says, hold on, look at רש"י. Rashi. חטאתו ואשמו של מצורע, chataso
v'ashamo shel metzora, רש"י Rashi says נתרבו בהדיא לנסכים במסכת מנחות פרק
שתי מדות. nitrabu b'hedya l'nesachim b'masechet Menachos perek shtei middos.
So actually the גמרא Gemara actually has a special דרשא drasha to
learn it out. So according to רש"י Rashi we start by knowing
that it brings נסכים nesachim and what he's doing is he's just
describing why that is, right? You understand it's a significant question here.
Do you say oh look I'm going to understand what this is
all based on and based on my טעמא דקרא ta'ama d'kra I'm
going to figure out what the הלכה halacha is going to be
by this other case that we don't know what the הלכה halacha
is yet, right? That's a little bit sounds like it, but no,
רש"י Rashi is saying this is really descriptive. It's not like it's
not you know he's not inferring this, he's describing why this is
an exception based on this reason that he is giving. Okay so
that's what he's saying so so he's really just explaining to you
here's why something's טעון נסכים ta'un nesachim and not because of this
reason. But let's see where the גמרא Gemara continues.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. איני eini is this really
true? ואמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן על שבעה דברים
נגעים באין v'amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan al shivah
devarim nega'im ba'in one minute, plagues come for you know leprosy, צרעת
tzara'as comes for seven sins. So therefore it is based on sin,
so your explanation doesn't make sense. The גמרא Gemara says no, התם
מנגעי הוא דאיכפר hatam mi-nega'ei hu d'ichpar
so there the נגע, nega, the צרעת, tzara'as, that is atoning for
whatever the sin was, הוא דאיכפר ליה. hu d'ichpar lei. כי מייתי
קרבן דקרבן לאו אכפרה דחטא ki mayti korban d'korban lav a-kaparah d'cheta
the קרבן korban isn't an atoning for the sin, the נגע nega
was the punishment for the sin, the קרבן korban is just לאשתריי
בקדשים הוא דקמייתי l'ishtarei b'kodashim hu d'ka-mayti that's just part of a
טהרה taharah process, right? That's not to atone for a sin. Okay,
so גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה ela me-ata if that's true, חטאת
נזיר תהא טעונה נסכים chatas nazir te-hei te'unah nesachim how about the
sin offering of a נזיר? nazir? Okay, לפי שאינה באה על חטא
lefi she-einah ba'ah al chet that's not for a sin, okay, and
that depends, right? But basically you're telling me that now any חטאת...
chatas... now here the גמרא Gemara makes it clear like again the
question is is the גמרא Gemara really saying let this be the
הלכה? halacha? Like is he really thinking we'll use your homiletic type
of explanation to actually say well then let's say that let's make
the הלכה halacha based on that, right? Is it really thinking that
again is the question is is it sort of working with a
דרשה drasha type of. קרא. cra. We can take your nice explanation
and actually then determine what the הלכה halacha will be. Or is
it saying no, no, no, we know what the הלכה halacha is.
There's no question that a חטאת chatas of a נזיר nazir does
not get נסכים. nesechim. Okay, we're not saying that we should actually
use your idea to change the הלכה. halacha. We're challenging your idea
based on the הלכה. halacha. Okay, how can you give this as
the explanation? It doesn't fit the data. Okay, we actually know that
a חטאת chatas of a נזיר nazir does not get נסכים, nesechim,
so goodbye to your explanation.
I think Dr. Lefko gave terms to that like a מדרש יוסר
midrash yoser and a מדרש midrash like there's these categories like specific
types, the function of different types of מדרש. midrash.
Right. Right. So I think that that's the question because I think,
if I'm remembering correctly, it's Rabbi Shimon who's דרשינן טעמא דקרא, darshinan
ta'ama dikra, right? Yes, it is. Right.
It's Rabbi Shimon who's דרשינן טעמא דקרא darshinan ta'ama dikra regarding אלמנה.
almanah. Right. And this is
Rabbi Shimon, Rabbi Yehuda, and Rabbi Shimon says דרשינן טעמא דקרא. darshinan
ta'ama dikra. And this is Rabbi Shimon. So actually Rabbi Shimon comes
from a position that in theory he might be prepared to actually
determine הלכה halacha based on his דרשה. drasha. So again, the interesting
question is, is the גמרא Gemara here really trying to determine whether
certain things should or should not get נסכים nesechim based on this?
Or does it already know what the data is and is just
challenging his explanation because it doesn't fit the data? Okay, so that
seems to be more—it seems to be more the second, but the
first one is not—is not necessarily ruled—to be categorically ruled out. So
the גמרא Gemara says, according to your logic, why does a חטאת
chatas of a נזיר nazir not have—it should have נסכים nesechim and
we know that it doesn't. It says no, סבר לה savar lah
כרבי אליעזר הקפר keRabbi Eliezer haKappar דאמר נזיר נמי חוטא הוא. d'amar
nazir nami chotei hu. He holds like Rabbi Eliezer haKappar that a
נזיר nazir is a sinner. So therefore the נזיר nazir is consistent
with his logic. Anything that's about חטא cheit doesn't have נסכים, nesechim,
and even the נזיר nazir doesn't have נסכים. nesechim. The data's consistent
with his explanation if we explain that a נזיר nazir is also
based on a sin. Okay. And then there's a long תוספות Tosafos
that tries to figure out, because there are different גמרות Gmaros that
talk about this idea that נזיר nazir is a sinner and some
גמרות Gmaros seem to say only a נזיר טמא nazir tamei is
a חוטא. chotei. Even according to Rabbi Eliezer haKappar. And other גמרות
Gmaros seem to say even because he let himself become טמא tamei
because when it—it stretches on, he regrets having accepted the נזירות. nezirus.
But a נזיר טהור nazir tahor maybe isn't a sinner. And there
are other גמרות Gmaros that say that even a נזיר טהור nazir
tahor according to this approach is a sinner just because he denied
himself the pleasure of wine. Even if it's a normal נזירות, nezirus,
even if he doesn't regret it, there's an element of a sin.
And תוספות Tosafos says this גמרא Gemara seems to say even a
נזיר טהור nazir tahor because the only נזיר nazir that brings an
animal חטאת, chatas, which is one that in theory could have נסכים,
nesechim, is the נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, not the נזיר טמא. nazir
tamei. So there's a long תוספות Tosafos trying to figure out whether
this approach applies only to a נזיר טמא nazir tamei or even
to a נזיר טהור. nazir tahor.
Yes, now my impression of the phrase שלא יהא חוטא נשכר shelo
yehei chotei niskar as a halachic principle in other contexts, is that
correct?
Yes, it is correct. Yeah, we do apply it
in a number of—exactly.
And here he's saying in theory that should have been applicable here
but there were more important things that override.
Yes, how about a woman who's given birth?
Right. So the question is that there too in all of these
explanations, right, logically we know, and a point that I've made a
lot is that the simple sense of a חטאת chatas is really
not even primarily about sin, but it's really about like
purification, cleansing. Sometimes the cleansing is a cleansing from sin, but the
חטאת chatas is often connected, you know, is often—when you have a
חטאת chatas for a יולדת, yoledes, right? You know, a חטאת chatas
for, you know,
for all these types of different people that are purifying themselves, is
that really for a sin or is it really just purification? So
the גמרא Gemara sometimes tries to make it about sin. Like well,
the יולדת, yoledes, when she's giving birth, she swears she's never going
to have sex with her husband again, etc. So the גמרא Gemara
could have asked those questions as well, right? I'm actually just looking
up here the רמב"ם, Rambam, hold on one minute.
Is it זב zav and זבה? zava? What? זב zav and זבה
zava too. Right.
זב zav and זבה zava too, exactly.
Hold
on. Quiet. Quiet.
Hold on.
Okay. Wish I had the link
exactly like, you know, the
גמרא Gemara online,
exactly.
So the
רמב"ם Rambam says אין טעונין נסכים אלא עולה בהמה ושלמים בלבד. ein
te'unun nesechim ela olah behemah veshelamim bilvad. And by the way, look
at תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos says טעונין נסכים, te'unun nesechim, אין לומר
דאינה טעונה נסכים משום דאינה בנדר ונדבה. ein lomar d'eina te'una nesechim
mishum d'eina b'neder u'nedavah.
There's a more basic reason. Forget this symbolism of חטא. cheit. Okay,
there's a general principle, although it's not a טעמא דקרא, ta'ama d'mikra,
it's just a law, the rule is the only thing that has
נסכים nesechim is a קרבן korban that's brought that's freewill, not obligatory.
And the only exception is the חטאת chatas and the אשם asham
of the מצורע. metzora.
On יום טוב Yom Tov and on שבת, Shabbos, that you bring
these נסכים, nesechim, those are freewill offerings?
Oh, but it's an עולה olah and it's a שלמים, shelamim, so
it's... Right, I'm sorry, it could be obligatory, but the category of
קרבן korban that can come בנדר ובנדבה. beneder uvenidava. Okay, you're right.
I was not being clear. An עולה olah and a שלמים shlamim
are categories that can come בנדר ובנדבה, beneder uvenidava, so even when
they're obligatory, like a מוסף, musaf, they have נסכים. nesachim. A חטאת
chatat that's always only obligatory, never by free will, doesn't have נסכים.
nesachim. The only exception being the חטאת chatat and the אשם asham
of a מצורע. metzora. So that's the real rule, meaning the real
rule is, no, חטאת chatat and אשם asham never, there's one exception.
But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, that's just a rule, it's not
an explanation, and it doesn't explain why אשם asham is an exception
why מצורע metzora is an exception. So I'm going to give you
an explanation, it's about sin and sin isn't appropriate and sin isn't
relevant by the מצורע, metzora, okay, but there's another way to frame
it, which is forget all this טעם דקרא, ta'am d'ikra, it's a
simple rule, חטאת chatat אשם asham don't get נסך. nesach. Okay, but
then again you have there is this exception of מצורע. metzora. Okay,
so and
if the רמב"ם Rambam says, אבל העוף האשמות והחטאות אין מביאים עמהם
נסכים חוץ מחטאת מצורע ואשמו שנתפרש נסכיהם בתורה, aval ha'of ha'ashamot vehachatatot
ein mevi'im imahem nesachim chutz mechataat metzora va'ashamo shenitparesh nischeihem batorah, okay,
so actually it's מפורש הפסוקים. meforash hap'sukim.
Anyway so that's what the רמב"ם Rambam says.
So is it מפורש הפסוקים? meforash hap'sukim? Are you looking for the
מצורע? metzora?
I got it right ahead over there. What does it say? והעלה
הכהן את העולה ואת המנחה המזבחה veha'ala hakohen et ha'olah ve'et haminchah
hamizbechah by over there.
By the מצורע? metzora?
Yeah, but it didn't say anything about the rest of the נסכים,
nesachim, so you know maybe that was what the question was.
All right, anyways fine. But anyway בקיצור, be-kitzer, so there seems to
be no question of the data and it's just a question about
like using is this a legitimate explanation? We're not trying to determine
what the הלכה halacha is. We know what the הלכה halacha is.
Is this a legitimate explanation of that? And if he was challenged
with the יולדת, yoledet, he probably would say that's also חטא cheit
based or something. Okay, let's continue in the גמרא. gemara. רבן גמליאל
אומר. Rabban Gamliel omer. כשם, ke-sheim, תניא. tanya. אמר להם רבן גמליאל
לחכמים. amar lahem Rabban Gamliel lachachamim. So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel gives
the reason of מאכל בהמה. ma'achal beheima. So why is he giving
a different why what you know why is he giving a different
reason so what would the חכמים chachamim reason be about the שעורים?
se'orim? So if you might remember there was an earlier explanation that
said the שעורים se'orim was because of since she made her lover
eat all of these delicacies so she's being fed this lowly food.
So אמר להם רבן גמליאל לחכמים, amar lahem Rabban Gamliel lachachamim, so
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said to the sages, סופרים, sofrim, which is
like scribes, interesting he's referring to them like that, הניחו לי ואדרשנו,
hanichu li ve'edreshenu, leave me alone, let me give a דרשה, drasha,
let me explain to you. It's interesting you wonder what's the dynamic
that he's referring to them as סופרים sofrim and he's saying הניחו
לי. hanichu li. So maybe one wonders like that whole phrase of
who's identified as the סופרים, sofrim, one wonders if like maybe the
idea is רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel fundamental role is like as a
תנא, tanna, right, he's the one that deals with like the area
of like הלכה, halacha, you know, but he and maybe there's others
that like specialize more in giving like you know דרש, drash, like
giving the symbolism and maybe again that's a category a group that's
identified as סופרים. sofrim. He's saying you know what, let let me
say the דרשה drasha here, like that's a nice explanation but I
have a different thing. But it sort of reminds you about a
case where like they say to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you know,
I forget who it is that says to him, but it says,
עקיבא עקיבא מה לך אצל אגדה כלך לך אצל נגעים ואהלות. Akiva
Akiva mah lecha etzel aggadah kelach lecha etzel nega'im ve'ohalot. Like עקיבא
Akiva you know
your specialty is like the hardest areas of הלכה, halacha, let us
do the אגדתא, aggadita, we know the answers. Was it רבי, Rabbi,
I don't think so. Anyway, but anyway but here you get a
similar type of a dynamic. Look, I know this isn't my specialty,
but I want to say my approach here. One minute. הניחו לי
ואדרשנו כמין חומר. hanichu li ve'edreshenu ke-min chomer. Now what does כמין
חומר ke-min chomer mean? רש"י Rashi says, if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, רש"י Rashi says בוטן בלע"ז boten bela'az I think, הוא שווה
זהב וחותמין בו שני טווי חלוקו לנוי. hu shoveh zahav vechotemin bo
shenei tavei chaluku lenoy. Like a nice like a like a nice
beautiful clasp, like something gold and beautiful. I'll give a beautiful explanation.
תוספות Tosafot says it might mean a pearl or a jewel. Anyway,
כמין חומר ke-min chomer is a phrase which somehow means I'll explain
it in a beautiful way. Okay, why? דשמיע ליה לרבי מאיר, deshamie
lei le-Rabbi Meir, he heard רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, now it seems
that the סופרים sofrim might be רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, דקאמר היא
האכילתו מעדני עולם, deka'amar hi hechilas-ho ma'adanei olam, she fed him the
delicacies, לפיכך קרבנה מאכל בהמה, lefichach korbanah ma'achal beheima, therefore she eats
the eating of animal, אמר ליה amar lei he said back, התינח
עשירה, hatinai ashirah, that's nice if she was a rich woman that
she fed her lover delicacies. עניה מאי איכא למימר, aniyah mai ika
lemeimar, let's say she was a poor woman, אלא ella so your
explanation doesn't fit that all cases, אלא ella mine fits all cases,
כשם שמעשיה מעשה בהמה כך קרבנה מאכל בהמה, kesheim shema'aseha ma'aseh beheima
kach korbanah ma'achal beheima, doesn't matter what she fed her lover, her
actions were fit for an animal, she's following after her lusts and
desires and so on, so her food is that like an animal
again of course completely like
dehumanizing her and assuming her guilt which is what we've been pointing
out all along. Charlie, what did you want to say?
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel could at times be dictatorial.
That's true. But I'm not sure that הניחו לי hanichu li is
that strong armed. Okay, let's take a look at the next משנה.
mishna. היה מביא פיילי של חרס ונותן לתוכה חצי לוג מים מן
הכיור. hayah meivi piyali shel cheres venoten letochah chatzi log mayim min
hakiyor.
So she brought a, so now the כהן, kohen, so there she
is, we spoke about the bringing of the מנחה. minchah. Okay, did
it say that the מנחה minchah was brought?
What did it say?
No, it didn't just say that it was brought yet, it just
described the
מנחה. minchah. After we see this, we'll go back to the point
תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* makes about what is the sequence here and how
does it or does it not match up to the sequence in
the תורה Torah *Torah*. But let's acknowledge that it says the מנחה
*mincha* is brought to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*, but
it has not yet been offered on the מזבח *mizbeiach*. Okay, and
now it act—and this actually is consistent with the תורה Torah *Torah*
because by the way, you know, the תורה *Torah* actually has the
bringing of the מנחה *mincha*, the offering up of it
after—after—no, the water is before the מנחה
*mincha*. But then it says again after:
וכתב את האלות האלה הכהן בספר ומחה אל מי המרים, והשקה את
האשה את מי המרים המאררים
ובאו בה המים המאררים למרים, ולקח הכהן מיד האשה את מנחת הקנאת
והניף את המנחה לפני ה'
והקריב אתה
אל המזבח, וקמץ הכהן
מן המנחה את אזכרתה והקטיר המזבחה ואחר ישקה את האשה את המים
*vechatav et ha'alot ha'eileh hakohein basefer umacha el mei hamarim, vehishka et
ha'ishah et mei hamarim hama'ararim uva'u vah hamayim hama'ararim lemarim, velakach hakohein
miyad ha'ishah et minchat hakinot vehenif et hamincha lifnei Hashem vehikriv otah
el hamizbeiach, vekamatz hakohein min hamincha et azkaratah vehiktir hamizbeicha ve'achar yashkeh
et ha'ishah et hamayim*.
So it's very like, right? So והשקת המים והייתה ונטמאה v'nitma-ah, *vehishkat
hamayim vehayta venitma'ah*. So it's confusing. It's like it says he writes
it and he makes her drink it, and he takes the מנחה
*mincha*, and then he makes her drink the water.
So why did it say before that he made her drink the
water? Was it before saying he's erasing it for the purpose of
making her drink the water? Anyway, it's confusing in the פסוקים *pesukim*,
which is why there's a debate in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* whether
the מנחה *mincha* is brought before or after the drinking of the
water, because it's pretty ambiguous in the פסוקים *pesukim* themselves. Okay, so
right now we have the מנחה *mincha* being brought, being brought to
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*, but we don't yet have
it having yet been offered up on the מזבח *mizbeiach*. And now
we're going to describe the drinking of the water. Okay. היה מביא
פיילי של חרס cheres. *haya meivi pili shel cheres*, he would brought
some type of a pottery vessel. Vial.
Picture here in, it's okay, all right, okay, original. ונותן לתוכו חצי
לוג מים מן הכיור *venotein letocho chatzi log mayim min hakiyor*,
he would put a half of a לוג *log*, which would be
like a, we normally drink a רביעית *revi'is* as a minimum size
of like קידוש *Kiddush* or whatever, it's like three ounces. So a
half of a לוג *log*, if that's a רביעית *revi'is* of a
לוג *log*, half a לוג *log* is double that, like six and
a half, seven ounces. Size of a normal like cup, you know,
it's like a six ounce cup. Not a tumble, like a normal
plastic cup is six ounces. Okay, there you go. ונותן לתוכו חצי
לוג מים מן הכיור *venotein letocho chatzi log mayim min hakiyor* from
the laver, from the, you know, the thing that they had in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* where they would pump the
water from. רבי יהודה אומר רביעית *Rabi Yehuda omer
revi'is*, it would only be a רביעית *revi'is* of water. כשם שמיעט
בכתב *keshem shemi'at bichtav*, we're going to see later that רבי יהודה
*Rabi Yehuda* is going to say that you wrote less on the
scroll, כך מיעט במים *kach mi'at bamayim*, so you have less that
you're writing that you're scraping, you have less water. Okay, now, נכנס
להיכל *nichnas laheichal*, the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* would—but no,
it doesn't say
כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*, the כהן *Kohen* would go into the היכל
*Heichal*, right, which is the inner sanctum, which is, you know, where
the שולחן *Shulchan* and the מנורה *Menorah* was. ופנה לימינו *ufana liyimino*,
he would
turn—because it speaks about מקרקע המשכן *mikarka hamishkan*, right? So, you know,
so that's, you know, and the אהל מועד *Ohel Mo'ed*, and that's
like the היכל
*Heichal*, right there when
there was like, you know, dust or dirt, it was on a
dirt floor. So let's see what he would do. נכנס להיכל ופנה
לימינו Nichnas l'Heichal ufana liyemino, *nichnas laheichal ufana liyimino*, he would turn
to his right. ומקום היה שם *umakom haya sham*, there would be
a little place on the floor of the היכל *Heichal*, אמה על
אמה *ama al ama*, a cubit by a cubit, טבלא של שיש
וטבעת הייתה קבועה בה *tavla shel shayish vetaba'at hayta kevu'ah bah*, and
there would be basically like a marble square covering up the ground,
right, it's the floor, it's a tile. It's a floor. It's a
Latin word.
What? What's Latin? טבלא *Tavla*.
*Tabla*, yes. *Tabla*,
yes. And there would be an and there would be a
ring, like an iron ring connected to the, you know, to this
טבלא *tabla*, to this
marble square, marble tile, so you could pick up the tile. Okay,
so וכשהוא מגביה *uchshehu magbi'ah*, I don't know how you didn't trip
over that, that same maybe was way in the corner. Anyway, וכשהוא
מגביה *uchshehu magbi'ah*, what? Recess.
Oh, that's interesting, a recessed,
oh I see, that's interesting. Okay, that's interesting. Okay. ולמה נתנו להיכל
*velama natnu laheichal*?
Because
we're going to learn it from the, it says "from the floor
of the משכן Mishkan. *Mishkan*," is, I mean, is the אהל מועד
*Ohel Mo'ed*, but we'll talk about that. Anyway, וכשהוא מגביה *uchshehu magbi'ah*,
okay, קבועה בה *kevu'ah bah*. וכשהוא מגביה *uchshehu magbi'ah*, and he lifts
it up, okay, and that he lifts it up, by the way.
Okay, ונוטל עפר מתחתיה *venoteil afar mitachteiha*, and he—so he lifts it
up and then he takes dirt from underneath the tile. ונותן לתוך
המים *venotein letoch hamayim*, and he puts it into the water, כדי
שייראה על המים *kedei sheyeira'eh al hamayim*, enough dirt that it appears
on the water like it floats to the top and is visible
on the water. שנאמר מן העפר אשר יהיה בקרקע min he'afar asher
yiheyeh be'karka המשכן יקח הכהן ונתן אל המים *shene'emar min ha'afar asher
yihyeh bekarka hamishkan yikach hakohein venatan el hamayim*, and he should put
it to the water. Okay, and now it says like this, גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. תנא פיילי של חרס חדשה דברי רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael.
*tana pili shel cheres chadasha divrei Rabi Yishmael*, it had to be
a new pottery vessel. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama? דרבי ישמעאל *mai ta'ama
deRabi Yishmael*, what's his reasoning? גמר כלי kli. כלי ממצורע *gamar kli
kli mimitzora*, he learns *kli kli* from the מצורע metzora *metzora*. מה
להלן חרס חדשה *ma lehalan cheres chadasha*. The same way a מצורע
metzora it's a new pottery, אף כאן חרס חדשה. af kan cheres
chadasha. Here's just the opposite. So, now there it says ושחט את
הצפור האחת אל כלי חרס, v'shachat et hatzippor ha'achat el kli cheres,
and here it says אל כלי חרס, el kli cheres, so you
put the water on כלי חרס, kli cheres, so therefore it's just
like that. Now how do we know there it has to be
new? והתם מנלן? v'hatam minalan? How do you know it has to
be new over there? דכתיב ושחט
את הצפור האחת
אל
כלי חרס על מים
חיים.
dich'tiv v'shachat et hatzippor
ha'achat el kli cheres
al mayim chayim. So what?
So what does that tell you? מה מים חיים שלא נעשתה בהן
מלאכה, mah mayim chayim shelo na'aseta bahen melacha, if it's living water,
it means it's never been used, it's straight from the ground, אף
כלי שלא נעשתה בו מלאכה. af kli shelo na'asta bo melacha. It
has to be a vessel that's never been used. That's an interesting
דרשה. drasha. אי מה להלן מים חיים אף כאן מים חיים, ee
mah lehalan mayim chayim af kan mayim chayim, okay, as long as
we're connecting it for the vessel purpose, and that we only get
from the idea of water, so let's say the water for the
סוטה Sotah also has to be מים חיים mayim chayim and it
can't be like well water or whatever. So the גמרא Gemara says,
רבי ישמעאל הכי נמי, Rabbi Yishmael hachi nami, you know what? No
problem. This is רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael, He actually says that the
כיור kiyor water is from an underground spring. דאמר רבי יוחנן מי
כיור רבי ישמעאל אומר מים חיים הן, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan mei kiyor
Rabbi Yishmael omer mayim chayim hen, it's tapping into an underground spring.
וחכמים אומרים משאר מימות הן, v'Chachamim omrim mishar meimot hen, it could
be from other collected waters, it doesn't have to be tapping into
an underground spring. Okay, איכא למפרך, ika l'mifrach, now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: איכא למפרך, ika l'mifrach, what, I can challenge learning
out a new vessel from מצורע metzora, to a new vessel for
the סוטה. Sotah. מה למצורע שכן טעון עץ ארז ואזוב ושני תולעת,
mah l'metzora sheken taun etz erez v'ezov u'shni tola'at, it has all
these other demands on the whole, you know, for the whole ritual.
So maybe it can have an additional demand that the vessel has
to be new? Maybe here it shouldn't. Or if you want to
also throw in the idea we're supposed to make everything very lowly
here, so maybe it should be new?
I know what you're gonna say. Again, you do that whole, I
understand, it's a new vessel, take an old one here. I understand,
but here it's a more formalist דרשה, drasha, not a more formalist
type of legal approach. So, even before getting to the reasons behind
it, it's just if there are more demands there, we can understand
a greater demand about the vessel. Here, we don't see those demands,
we shouldn't assume the same degree of, the same criteria. What?
Even though they're as far as low, but they're also going to
put השם's Hashem name into it, so maybe in that sense it
should be,
oh that's maybe for respect for God's name, that's interesting. Okay, so
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רבא אמר קרא בכלי
חרס. Amar Rava amar kra bichli cheres. No, here it says that
you put it בכלי חרס bichli cheres and it doesn't say in
a כלי חרס, kli cheres, question about what else it should have
said. But anyway that somehow refers to
like the כלי חרס kli cheres that you know about, כלי שאמרתי
לך כבר, kli she'amarti lecha kvar, a vessel that's referenced elsewhere, and
therefore that is referenced, you know, earlier in the תורה by the
מצורע metzora, which we know is a new one. Again, it's a
little unclear, like what else should the תורה have said? So רש"י
Rashi just says like, it could have said, what could it have
said?
מדלא
כתיב ולקח כלי חרס ונתן בו. mid'lo ktiv v'lakach kli cheres v'natan
bo. It could have said ונתן בו, v'natan bo, and it says
ונתן בכלי חרס, v'natan bichli cheres, so somehow it means just like
the other כלי. I don't know. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, anyway that's
רבי ישמעאל, it has to be a new vessel.
אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Now רש"י Rashi reads this next line going
even according to the חכמים. Chachamim. לא שנו, lo shanu, when did
we say for the חכמים Chachamim it doesn't have to be new?
אלא שלא נתאכמו פניו, ela shelo nitachmu panav, if it hasn't like
blackened. Okay, it could be a used pottery vessel, but it can't
have been so old that it's, that the, you know, appearance is
blackened. אבל נתאכמו פניו, aval nitachmu panav, once it's blackened, פסולין, psulin,
it's invalid. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? דומיא דמים, dumya d'mayim, at least,
forget that we learn it out from מצורע, metzora, it doesn't have
to be מים חיים mayim chayim like מצורע, metzora? but from with
its, but it is, you put the water into the vessel. So
at least we connect it to the mention of water in the
פרשה parsha of, of סוטה Sotah itself. It has to be somewhat
like water. What does that mean somewhat like water?
This vial? You're not bringing it from home, the husband and wife.
Yeah, but it's not, but but maybe it's owned by the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash, I don't think so. I don't think it's not
able to be a כלי שרת kli sharet if it's חרס. What?
Or that's a מחלוקת. machlokes. Anyway, I, oh no, I think everybody
agrees כלי חרס kli cheres can't be כלי שרת. kli sharet. Yeah,
presumably. They cook with it anyway, right? For this purpose. Okay, אלא
שלא נתאכמו פניו, ela shelo nitachmu panav, אבל נתאכמו פניו, aval nitachmu
panav, פסולין. psulin. If it's blackened it's invalid. מאי טעמא? דומיא דמים.
dumya d'mayim. מה מים שלא נשתנו אף כלי שלא נשתנה. mah mayim
shelo nishtanu af kli shelo nishtaneh. Because at least has to be
like the water and therefore it has to be not נשתנה. nishtaneh.
Now תוספות Tosafot, actually points out that you know there's another גמרא
Gemara actually by עבודה זרה Avoda Zara that says because the גמרא
Gemara has all question about the way we know you can't have
like בישול עכו"ם, bishul akum, things cooked by non-Jews. And one basis
that the גמרא Gemara says is because משה Moshe says אוכל בכסף
תשברני ואכלתי ומים בכסף תתן לי ושתיתי. Ochel bakesef tishbereni v'achalti u'mayim
bakesef titen li v'shatiti. Like when they're passing through, you know, the
other nations. So it says כמים. kemayim. If you want food it
has to be like water. שלא נשתנה. shelo nishtaneh. It can't have
been processed, it can't, it has to be raw, okay, it can't
have been so, so then the גמרא Gemara challenges it because it
doesn't exactly fit all the parameters of בישול עכו"ם, bishul akum, it's
not like anything cooked is not good. Anyway, so if you look
at רש"י Rashi at תוספות, Tosafot מה מים שלא נשתנו, mah mayim
shelo nishtanu, תוספות Tosafot says like this halfway down line starting with
תימה. teimah. תימה לרבי מה ישנא דהכא אמר מה מים
שלא נשתנו פרק ב' דמסכת עבודה זרה לא מסקי הכי גבי בישולי
עובדי כוכבים.
Teimah l'rabbi mah yishnah d'hacha amar mah mayim shelo
nishtanu
perek bet d'masechet Avoda Zara lo maski hachi gabei bishulei ovdei kochavim.
It doesn't make such sense. Now maybe it fits here and it
doesn't fit there. But anyway, תוספות Tosafot says, ונראה דהכא נמי אסמכתא
בעלמא הוא v'nireh dehacha nami asmachta b'alma hu וליכא לפסולא דרבנן. v'leka
l'psula d'rabbanan. Fine. This whole idea that it can't have been like
changed, the vessel, and even it doesn't have to be old, it
can't be blackened, it can't have transformed, it's all rabbinic. Bottom line
is, right, all the Torah says is כלי חרס. kli cheres. It'd
be funny that we start coming up with this idea it has
to be like a כלי חרס kli cheres but it can't have
somehow changed, be very different than the way it was originally made.
But anyway, so תוספות Tosafot says it's an אסמכתא. asmachta.
תוספות Tosafot is also implying that בישול עכו״ם bishul akum was also
דרבנן. derabbanan.
Oh well בישול עכו״ם bishul akum is דרבנן, derabbanan, but that's not
his point. His point is that the דרשה's drasha not a great
דרשה. drasha. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
But you can't even have colors either? Like let's say you wanted
to paint it? You can't do it?
Yeah, I know. So that's the question. I don't know, I mean
it sounds like it's supposed to be natural,
right? No, Michael's asking a different question. נתאכמו nisachmu means it get
blackened from use. But Michael's asking a different question, how much do
we have to say it has to be in its original condition?
Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. בעי רבא: baei
Rava: now, נתאכמו והחזירן לתוך כבשנה אש ונתלבנו מהו? nisachmu vehachziran letoch
kivshana es venisalbenu mahu? Let's say you had the vessel you were
going to use and it got blackened and then you refired it.
So what's the הלכה? halacha? מי אמרינן כיון דאדחו אדחו? mi amrinan
kivan de'idchu idchu? Once it was in a status of being fit
to be used for the service and became pushed away, it cannot
be reused, which is
funny because if you made a totally brand new vessel, that would
be fine. But this isn't a brand new vessel. This is a
vessel that might have on it the stigma of being rejected. So
if you were to brand a new vessel, that's fine, but a
rejected one that now has been somehow fixed, it still has that
stigma of being rejected. That's a concept of דיחוי. dichui. And once
something has been rejected, it can never be reused for מצוה mitzvah
purposes. או דילמא? odilma? Or do we say no, כיון דהדר הדר?
kivan de'hadar hadar? No, now it's back to be usable. Now what
does that mean? Does it mean that we don't hold of the
principle of דיחוי? dichui? Or does it mean that it was never
a real נדחה nidcheh because it was really seen as like a
tangential reason it wasn't usable? It wasn't sort of central to its
identity maybe? Or was something that was able to be changed? Like
a מום עובר? mum over? Right, it was like a מום עובר,
mum over, was something that was able to be changed. Or you
could say another thing. Maybe it's פנים חדשות באו לכאן? panim chadashot
bau lekan? You're refiring it, maybe it's like a completely new vessel.
Okay, so what do we say? So תא שמע: ta shema: come
and hear. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: עץ ארז ואזוב ושני
תולעת, etz erez ve'ezov ushni tolaat, you have the various things that
you're going to use for the whole thing of the מצורע, metzora,
right, the עץ ארז etz erez or the פרה אדומה parah adumah
actually. Okay, you have the hyssop and the cedar and the red
string. שהשיאו בהן קופתו לאחוריו, shehishu bahem kupahto le'achorav, that you basically
used it
to hold a string to hold your bag to carry your bag
on your back.
פסולין: psulin: it's invalid. So now רש״י Rashi says why is it
invalid? Because you're using it for מלאכה melacha and you're not supposed
to do מלאכה. melacha. So רש״י Rashi says it sounds like מלאכה
melacha doesn't, well let's take a look. The גמרא's Gemara going to
assume it's invalid because you changed them, you bent them, they're not
in their pristine state. Okay, well let's first read the גמרא Gemara
and then I'll talk about the מלאכה. melacha. So והתם הדרי ופשטי,
vehatam hadrei u-pash-ti, why is that invalid? Even if you bent it,
you can straighten it out. So you see that even though you
straightened it out, it remains invalid. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
התם דאיקלף איקלופי. hatam de'iklaf iklufei. There it could be not just
really bent in a way that it can't be restraightened. So therefore
it can't be fixed. That's why it remains invalid. But this can
be fixed, maybe it becomes, it can become valid once again. So
רש״י Rashi by the way is bothered like why is the גמרא
Gemara focusing on the fact that it's bent? Shouldn't it be a
problem that you do מלאכה? melacha? And we normally assume that things
associated right with the פרה אדומה parah adumah are things that you
can't do מלאכה melacha with. So if you take a look at,
actually no, I think the question is is this talking about פרה
אדומה parah adumah or is this talking about מצורע?
metzora I
think he's talking about מצורע, metzora. yeah. To be, I think תוספות
Tosafot, refers to the מצורע metzora. case. So if you take a
look at תוספות, Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says like this: והתם
דהדרי ופשטי, vehatam de'hadrei u-pash-ti, פירש רש״י מדלא קתני שנעשה בהן מלאכה
שמע מינה לא קפיד אשינוי קפיד. peirash Rashi midelo katani shena'asa bahen
melacha shema mina lo kapid ashinui kapid. Okay, that the מלאכה melacha
isn't a problem. וקשיא לרבי: vekashya l'rabbi: this is difficult, מתוספתא דנגעים,
mi-Tosefta de-Nega'im, פרק אין מצורע. Perek Ein Metzora. רבי אליעזר אומר עץ
ארז ואזוב ושני תולעת שנאמר בתורה שלא נעשה בהם מלאכה. Rabbi Eliezer
omer etz erez ve'ezov ushni tolaat shene'emar ba-Torah shelo na'asa bahem melacha.
אלמא דמלאכה פסולה בהן, alma de'melacha psula bahen, ורבי אליעזר גופיה, ve'Rabbi
Eliezer gufei, the same רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says מלאכה's melacha a
problem. So how does the גמרא Gemara, focusing on whether it's bent
or not bent, it actually is a problem that you used it
for the strap for your knapsack? And maybe it's not just
the מלאכה, melacha, maybe על ידי מלאכה al yedei melacha it gets
all messed up and
that's, no, because there's a concept of נעשה בהן מלאכה. na'asa bahen
melacha. Anyway, so תוספות Tosafot doesn't know the answer. How does the
גמרא Gemara sort of ignoring the מלאכה melacha issue? But also the
fact that תוספות's Tosafot quoting the נגעים Nega'im makes it clear that
we're talking in the context of the עץ ארז etz erez and
the אזוב ezov for the מצורע. metzora So somehow this is the
question about if it somehow became somehow bent, disfigured, it's a physical
problem that can't be fixed. Now, how does this fit into general
דיחוי dichui discussions? Like isn't there a general discussion about דיחוי? dichui?
So again, maybe part is because this is not something that's been
sanctified. It's something that's going to be used similar to the מצורע.
issue in some type of a ritual, a ritual in the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash? but it's not a קרבן, korban, right? So therefore,
I mean in the מצורע you even have, you even have it
like outside of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, So what do you
do about these things that are somehow ritual and somewhat מקדש Mikdash
connected etc. but not קרבנות? korbanot? To what degree do you have
an idea of דחוי? dichui? Like there's a whole discussion in the
גמרא, do you have an idea of נדחה nidcha by objects of
a מצוה? mitzvah? Something like a הדס hadas that had berries and
then you picked the berries from it. Like do you have an
idea of דחוי? dichui? The classic דחוי dichui is by a קרבן.
korban. What about a מצוה mitzvah object? What about a מקדש Mikdash
ritual object that's not a קרבן? korban? So that seems to be
like one possible way of understanding. Or as I said, another possible
way of understanding is maybe something that by its very nature is
a transitory problem fundamentally does not create דחוי. dichui. Okay, and
תוספות Tosafot, raises this, broadens this, so look at תוספות, Tosafot נתחממו
והחזירו לתוך כבשת האש מהו, Nischammu vehachzirum letoch kivshat ha'esh mahu, תוספות
Tosafos says, תימה מאי שנא דקא מיבעיא ליה הכא בנראה ונדחה וחזר
ונראה, Teima mai shna d'ka mibaya lei hacha benireh venidcha vechazar venireh,
right that's the normal phrase. It was fit, it was נדחה, nidcha,
became fit
again. והא בפרק ב' דלולב הגזול קא מיבעיא ליה ולא איפשטא. Veha
b'perek beis d'Lulav HaGazul ka mibaya lei velo ipshata. First of all
it's a general question. ועוד מאי שנא מהא דאמר בזבחים בגדי כהונה
שהיו מלוכלכין או מטוטשין. Ve'od mai shna meha d'amar biZevachim bigdei kehuna
shehayu meluchlachin o metutashin. Let's say you had rent or soiled garments
of בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, ועבר ועבד עבודתו פסולה, ve'avar ve'avad avodato
psula, it's invalid. ואפילו הכי אם כיבס טישטוש וגיהוץ שלהן, Ve'afillu hachi
im kibus tishtush vegihutz shelahen, if you clean them, put them into
the cleaners, חזרו לכשרן כדאיתא בברייתא פרק
המזבח מקדש בגדי כהונה אין עושין בהן מעשה מחט אלא מעשה אורג.
chazru l'keshran k'deita bivraisa perek HaMizbeach Makdish bigdei kehuna ein osin bahen
ma'aseh machat ela ma'aseh oreg.
You, נתגאלו אין מכבסין אותן לא בנתר ולא באהל. nisga'alu ein mechabsin
osan lo beneser velo be'ohel. ופרכינן הא במים מכבסין Ufarcheinan ha bamayim
mechabsin etc. Anyway, the גמרא says אלמא דמכבסין אותן, alma d'mechabsin osan,
you can actually, you can actually send them to the laundry. Okay,
now of course you could make distinctions, right? There dirt is maybe
something that is more, you know, ethereal? Like here maybe if you
have to put it into the fire to get out the black,
maybe that's considered more of a permanent type of a thing than
just getting out the soil which is seen as an extraneous thing
that's cleaving onto it. But anyway, and again it's interesting, and you
know, בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna are sanctified, right? This, this isn't sanctified,
so it's again interesting in this whole world of נדחה. nidcha. It
starts with a קרבן, korban, right? But what do you, how do
you translate to things that are maybe a מצוה, mitzvah, not a
קרבן, korban, מקדש Mikdash ritual but not sanctified, בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna
which are sanctified but the problem is less permanent, right? All these
different permutations of this concept of נדחה, nidcha, yes.
Interesting symbolic thinking too in this section of סוטה, Sotah, the whole
question of what can be
redeemed and back, you know she's גירות, geirut, right? And we talk
about, you know it's so funny because people like talking about like
trial by ordeal, right? So the ordeal, is it a water ordeal
or a fire ordeal? Right, here you have a fire that basically
is like a cleansing and a restoring type of a process. That's
a nice idea. Okay, let's finish to the bottom of the דף.
daf.
נכנס להיכל ופנה לימינו, goes into ההיכל haHeichal and makes a right
turn. מאי טעמא דאמר mar כל פינות שאתה פונה לא יהיו אלא
דרך ימין. Whenever you turn in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you
always turn to the right, for the right is seen as the
stronger direction, is the more symbolically meaningful direction.
And right, by the way, you know, that's why when like you
take out the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and you like you make
the rotations around, you know it also sort of figures out like
if you're facing the בימה bimah and you'd be moving to your
right, right? So then you're moving in a counter-clockwise direction, right? So
that's why you're sort of always sort of moving by the ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah, you're sort of going in that counter-clockwise direction.
Okay, so also when the כלה kallah goes around the חתן. chasan.
מקום
היה שם אמה על אמה. Makom haya sham ama al ama. תנו
רבנן ומן העפר אשר יהיה בקרקע המשכן. Tanu rabbanan umin he'afar asher
yihiyeh be'karka haMishkan. From the dirt, the dust that's on the ground
of the
משכן. Mishkan יכול יתקין מבחוץ ויכניס, Yachol yaskin mibachutz veyachnis, maybe you
can just take dirt from outside, it doesn't you know and put
it there? תלמוד לומר בקרקע המשכן. Talmud lomar be'karka haMishkan. No, it
has to be on the ground, you can't just bring dirt from
the outside. אי בקרקע המשכן יכול יחפור בקרדומית, Ee be'karka haMishkan yachol
yachpor bekardomit, maybe if it has to be from the dirt, maybe
it really needs to be from the natural ground that's underneath the
משכן Mishkan. and you have to take a shovel? תלמוד לומר אשר
יהיה. Talmud lomar asher yihiyeh. No, it just happens to be on
the ground of the משכן. Mishkan Right, it doesn't say ומן העפר
של קרקע המשכן. umin he'afar shel karka haMishkan. אשר יהיה, Asher yihiyeh,
that happens to be, so you just lay some dirt on the
קרקע karka from beforehand. הכיצד יש שם הבה אין שם תן שם.
Ha keitzad yesh sham havei ein sham ten sham. If there's dirt
that's there that can be collected, use the dirt that's there. If
there's no dirt that's there that's collected, the ground is hard, it's
not loose or whatever, I don't know if it would be אסור
assur to dig with a shovel, but who wants to be bringing
a shovel into the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash. So pre-lay some dirt
there so that it'll be able to be found when the אשר
יהיה asher yihiyeh happens to be there.
Okay, and we need to, but it needs to be in, it
needs to be on the קרקע המשכן.
karka haMishkan. Presumably it can't be on the tile, it has to,
that's an interesting thing, right? What, that is an interesting thing. And
what is defined as בקרקע המשכן? Karka Hamishkan? You might say that
by the time you get to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash the
קרקע karka is no longer the dirt, the קרקע karka is the
actual tile floor. And just put the dirt on top of the
tile. So it is interesting that we're assuming though that you have
to actually put the dirt on the dirt underneath the tile, on
the ground underneath the tile. Okay, תניא אידך, tanya idach, we taught
in another
ברייתא. braita. ומעפר אשר יהיה, u'me'afar asher yiheyeh, מלמד שהיה מתקין מבחוץ
ומכניס. melamed she'haya matkin mibachutz u'machnis. Okay, so actually this ברייתא braita
actually says it should have stopped before בקרקע המשכן. be'karka hamishkan. אשר
יהיה, asher yiheyeh, any dirt, you don't even have to lay it
on the ground, just take dirt from the outside. That's a pretty
creative read of the פסוק. posuk. ומעפר אשר יהיה, u'me'afar asher yiheyeh,
take from any dirt that's there, you could even bring dirt from
outside. So then what do you do with the word בקרקע המשכן?
be'karka hamishkan? So there we say that means something else. בקרקע המשכן,
be'karka hamishkan, איסי בן יהודה אומר להביא קרקע שילה נוב וגבעון ובית
עולמים. Issi ben Yehuda omer le'havi karka Shilo Nov u'Givon u'Veis Olamim.
Yes, absolutely, so בקרקע המשכן, be'karka hamishkan, again it's funny, what's the
ריבוי? ribbuy? Well, maybe because it didn't have to say משכן Mishkan?
at all, it could have just said מן העפר אשר יהיה min
he'afar asher yiheyeh. בקרקע or מן העפר אשר יהיה. Why did it
add משכן? Mishkan So it's funny funny, משכן Mishkan you would think
is a limiting word, you know, but maybe it's saying no like
משכן Mishkan. is any place where there's some idea of a משכן.
Mishkan, So even if it's in נוב וגבעון Nov u'Givon and obviously
בית עולמים, Beis Olamim, בית עולמים Beis Olamim isn't a משכן, Mishkan
it's a מקדש. Mikdash. Okay, so you might have thought on the
one hand maybe on the one hand it's only when it's in
its transitory state, only a משכן Mishkan, not a מקדש, Mikdash, or
you might have thought only when it's something that is like, you
know, really like represents similar to the משכן, Mishkan. נוב וגבעון. Nov
u'Givon. רש"י Rashi is actually very bothered by the fact that it
says נוב וגבעון Nov u'Givon here, because נוב וגבעון Nov u'Givon did
not have a full status of a משכן. Mishkan, Why not? If
you look at רש"י Rashi on the bottom of ט"ו עמוד ב',
Tes Vov Amud Beis, רש"י Rashi says the following:
four lines from the bottom. ולא גריס לרבות שילה נוב וגבעון. v'lo
garis l'rabos Shilo Nov u'Givon. Why not? ובית עולמים דשילה פשיטא דמשכן
הוא. u'Veis Olamim d'Shilo peshita d'Mishkan hu. You don't have to be
מרבה marbeh שילה. Shilo. שילה Shilo was exactly the משכן, Mishkan right?
Meaning שילה Shilo was the exact משכן Mishkan. from the from, you
know, that they had in the wilderness relocated to שילה. Shilo. Obviously
that's the same. There, no, נוב וגבעון Nov u'Givon are different in
one direction, going down, and מקדש Mikdash is different in another direction,
going up. Right, מקדש Mikdash is permanent, it's different than the משכן.
Mishkan, נוב וגבעון Nov u'Givon are different in the following way. ולא
צריך לריבויי דעיקר קרא בנוב וגבעון אין משקין את הסוטות. v'lo tzarich
l'ribbuye d'ikar kra b'Nov u'Givon ein mashkin es ha'sotos. נוב וגבעון Nov
u'Givon actually you wouldn't do the סוטה Sotah ritual there. Why not?
דבמה הוה ולא היה שם ארון אלא מזבח הנחשת לבדו. d'bamah hava
v'lo hayah sham aron ela mizbe'ach ha'nechoshes levado. That even though it
was basically just like a central במה, bamah, okay, it was not
forbidden to worship on your private במה bamah at that time, it
was not the only central the the single place of worship, so
it did not have that same power of the משכן, Mishkan okay,
and even the ארון aron wasn't there. And therefore רש"י Rashi says
and you would not do in נוב וגבעון, Nov u'Givon, you would
not do private types of rituals, okay, you would only do communal
rituals. So the ארון aron was right there, it was, no, the
פלשתים Plishtim took it right down. Whatever, but it wasn't stayed it
wasn't centered there. Okay, so anyway so תוספות Tosafos says, if you
look at תוספות Tosafos top of ט"ו עמוד א', Tes Vov Amud
Aleph, רש"י גריס להביא קרקע בית עולמים ושיבש הגירסא, Rashi garis le'havi
karka Beis Olamim v'shibesh ha'girsa, right, because שילה נוב וגבעון משום דנוב
וגבעון אין משקין סוטות משום דהוי מנחת יחיד שאין קבוע לה זמן.
Shilo Nov u'Givon mishum d'Nov u'Givon ein mashkin sotos mishum d'havei minchas
yachid she'ein kavua lah zman. And תוספות says ותימה ששיבש משום קושיא
זו. v'teima she'shibesh mishum kushya zu. He completely corrupted the גירסא, girsa,
he just, you know, erased it because of this
question. דילמא קסבר איסי בן יהודה כרבי יהודה דאמר פרק בא סימן
כל שבציבור וביחיד מקריבים באוהל מועד שבמדבר מקריבים באוהל מועד שבגלגל ואין
חילוק ביחיד dilma kasavar Issi ben Yehuda k'Rabbi Yehuda d'amar perek ba
siman kol she'be'tzibbur u'v'yachid makrivim b'ohel mo'ed she'bamidbar makrivim b'ohel mo'ed she'bagilgal
v'ein chilluk b'yachid etc. etc. So maybe there is an opinion that
you could do a יחיד yachid type of a ritual and קרבן
korban in נוב וגבעון, Nov u'Givon, so you could do סוטה Sotah
in נוב וגבעון Nov u'Givon as well. Okay, so it's an interesting
question of would they have done it in נוב וגבעון, Nov u'Givon,
could you do these private types of rituals there? But you also
need a פסוק posuk to include even a more permanent, a בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. you know, maybe it was only something in a
transitory state. Maybe when things are a little bit more permanent it's
funny to keep on doing these types of, you know, I don't
know, testing rituals or whatever. Anyway, so you need a פסוק. posuk.
But not to tell you that the dirt had to be on
the floor, just to tell you it works in other forms of
the משכן Mishkan as well. איסי בן מנחם, Issi ben Menachem, let's
just read the last line. איסי בן מנחם אומר אינו צריך. Issi
ben Menachem omer eino tzarich. You don't need to include בית עולמים.
Beis Olamim. ומה u'mah and this also reinforces רש"י Rashi that the
emphasis is on בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, ומה בטומאה קלה לא חלק
הכתוב. u'mah b'tumah kalah lo chillak ha'kasuv. When it comes to the
issue of that being טמא, tamei, you're not allowed to be in
the משכן Mishkan, and we learn from a פסוק posuk you also
can't go into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, when you're טמא. tamei.
So בטומאת אשת איש חמורה, b'tumah eshis ish chamurah, with the more
weighty טומאה tumah of adultery, לא כל שכן lo kol shekein how
much more so should that be equally relevant in the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. I'll go back to that in a minute, but let's
just finish the thought. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר בקרקע המשכן? im
kein mah talmud lomar b'karka ha'mishkan? If קרקע משכן Karka Mishkan doesn't
have to include בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. what does it include? שלא
יביא מתוך קופתו, she'lo yavi mitoch kuppaso, what we said before, that
you can't take out of a basket, you have to put it
on the floor. So here there's a debate, does the dirt have
the dirt doesn't have to... be natural to there, but does it
have to be pre-laid on the floor or not? One opinion is
no, sort of stops the פסוק posuk before you get to קרקע
המשכן, karka ha'mishkan, and the other read is much more reasonable. No,
you actually have to get dirt from the floor. And neither says
it has to be בדיעבד. bedieved. Everybody says you can pre- at
least you can pre-lay it, but one opinion says you don't even
have to pre-lay it. Now, I do want to just end by
saying this קל וחומר kal v'chomer is very strange. Like, okay, I
get that if you say that if you can't do טומאה קלה,
tumah kallah, you know, we already know you can't go to the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. which is- if you can't bring- a טמא
tamei person can't go to the משכן, he can't go to the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So certainly a more weighty טמא tamei person
can't go into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. That I get. Okay,
but we're not saying that in multiple directions. Number one, A, just
okay, we're using the idea of טומאה tumah by אשת איש. eishet
ish. I mean the פסוק posuk says,
right, ונטמאה, right, and she became- you know, she stepped out on
him and she became טמאה. t'mei-ah. But that never translates into entering
into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. There's never a הלכה halacha that
a woman who is known to have committed adultery is אסור asur
to enter into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. That concept of טומאה
tumah is a very distinct concept, it's a sin moral concept of
טומאה tumah that is very distinct from the הלכות halachos of entering
into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So saying if a normal טמא
tamei person can't go in, a weighty טומאה tumah of אשת איש,
eishet ish, I assume it's weighty because it's more moral and sin
related, but nevertheless it doesn't mean that they can't enter the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, And number two is we're not talking about entering
the בית המקדש. We're talking about a weighty טומאה tumah of אשת
איש eishet ish should certainly be able to be processed in the
סוטה Sotah ritual in the בית המקדש. What's the קל וחומר? kal
v'chomer? If normal טומאה tumah is kept out of the בית המקדש,
then a weighty טומאה tumah of אשת איש eishet ish should certainly
be able to undergo the סוטה Sotah ritual. Like what? It's a
very strange קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, but it is fascinating the comparison
of these two טומאות tumos which really come from very different spheres
and making some type of, you know, analogy between them. Okay.